Okay. All right, good. So if we can call it back to
yesterday,
we started talking about the לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin and whether or
not there were מזוזות, mezuzot, right? There and a whole other places
in the עזרה, Azarah,
which was a מחלוקת. machloket. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda had
said—well, first the—I'll just circle back to that תנו רבנן. tanna rabbanan.
They said all the לשכות lishkot in the מקדש Mikdash did not
have a מזוזה mezuzah except for the לשכת פרהדרין, Lishkat Parhedrin, because
which—reason why it had one, because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol had
his, like, you know, apartment in there for at least for a
week anyway. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said,
what—why did that make a difference? There are other לשכות lishkot that
had בתי דירה, batei dirah, basically, and they didn't have מזוזה. mezuzah.
Okay, he doesn't disagree that the לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin had one,
but if it's just a matter of it being a—I brought yours
here. Oh, sorry. It's over there.
Over there. That's yours over there.
Yeah, you can use this today.
It's mine, but you can use it today. Thanks.
Anyway,
so—so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said if it's a matter of a
בית דירה, beit dirah, then that shouldn't have made the לשכת פרהדרין
Lishkat Parhedrin any different, because there are other places that had a
בית דירה beit dirah and didn't have a מזוזה. mezuzah. But so
then
why did this one have a מזוזה? mezuzah? Because everyone agrees it
had a מזוזה. mezuzah. So רבא Rava said it was a גזירה,
gezeirah, right?
So—and what was the גזירה? gezeirah? So then what we ended with
yesterday was שלא יאמרו כהן גדול חבוש בבית האסורים, shelo yomru Kohen
Gadol chavush bebeit ha-asurim, right? Just—don't—you know, isn't seen—because if you don't
say it's really the type of place that, you know, is habitable
all the rest of the year, and he's there like, you know,
בעל כרחו, ba'al korcho, and you don't want to kind of give
out—give off that impression that he's there against his will, like jail
so to speak. So since we started talking about מזוזה, mezuzah, that's
what we're going to talk about all the rest of today and
I think tomorrow too.
So we'll—we'll dive right in. I wanted to get a משנה ברורה
Mishnah Berurah and—or שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, but it was actually locked
downstairs. I didn't get the opportunity to do so, so
hopefully at some point the בית מדרש Beit Midrash will open.
I just—anybody reading those books, you know?
Yeah, right.
The רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel approach.
בשלמא, Beshlamah, we learn הלכה. halakhah.
So that's what I want to do. I mean, I have some
stuff here, but—okay, anyway, so מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן? man tanna
lehu detanna rabbanan? Now on י"א ע"א, Yud-Alef Amud-Alef, כל השערים
שהיו שם לא היה להם מזוזה. kol hashearim she-hayu sham lo hayah
lahem mezuzah. So now we're talking about the לשכות, lishkot, but you
know, as we know,
you have to put on מזוזות—מזוזות ביתך beitcha, ובשעריך, uvisharecha
right? So שערים—your—your shearim gate. So what about the gates of the—you
know, בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Or gates just in general, which—which we'll
talk about. And I'll just—you know, just let you know that don't
take anything being yet axiomatic, because, you know, there'll very likely be
a statement that
contradicts. It'll be very confusing in that sense. Hopefully
it's—not—not just me, but it's the גמרא Gemara too, that you know,
that like just keep reversing itself. So we'll have to deal with
those contradictions and the גמרא Gemara itself will point that out, so
just, you know, be aware that we'll be reversing ourselves a whole
bunch of times. So it may be hard to keep a score,
but if you're confused, it's just the way it is just due
to changes of opinion. Anyway, כל השערים שהיו שם לא היה להם
מזוזה. kol hashearim she-hayu sham lo hayah lahem mezuzah. So all the
שערים—and shearim רש"י Rashi points out that it's שער מזרח עזרה Sha'ar
Mizrach Azarah particularly, but nevertheless, except for שער ניקנור. Sha'ar Nikanor. So
you know, the שער ניקנור Sha'ar Nikanor was—was, you know, in the—I
think that was the one that separating the—probably even have a picture
in your—it had the steps. Yeah, that was the one that—you know,
that basically got you from עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, you know, into
עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, which is a very narrow space of like
eleven אמות. amot. So
anyway, שלפנים ממנו—so she-lifnim mimennu within that was לשכת פרהדרין, Lishkat Parhedrin,
and remember like we weren't exactly sure where the לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat
Parhedrin was, but it was really kind of right around there. So—so
that had a מזוזה. mezuzah.
Okay, fine. So לימא רבנן היא ולא רבי
יהודה?
leima rabbanan hi velo
Rabbi Yehuda? Because—so shall we say that that's the רבנן's Rabbanan opinion,
not רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Why would that not be רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? דרבי יהודה, dee Rabbi Yehuda, היא גופא גזירה, hi gufah
gezeirah, ואנן נקום ונגזר גזירה לגזירה? va'anan nekum venigzar gezeirah legezeirah? So
having a whole מזוזה mezuzah in לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin itself is—is
a גזירה. gezeirah. So now you're going to put a מזוזה mezuzah
on the שער sha'ar that leads to where לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin
would be? I mean, that's—why would—he wouldn't take it that far if
he thinks that you don't really need a מזוזה mezuzah to begin
with, right?
So it would not be according to his opinion. So now, אפילו
תימא רבי יהודה, afilu teima Rabbi Yehuda, maybe even רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda would agree, because כולה חד גזירה היא, kulla chad gezeirah hi,
because it's—it's all like the same idea, because once you're already making
a מזוזה mezuzah for the לשכת פרהדרין, Lishkat Parhedrin, you'll make it
for anything that's associated with it, so to speak, leads up to
it,
as was in that realm. Okay, so now we're going to discuss
the obligation of putting on מזוזות.
mezuzot And remember what is—the גזירה, gezeirah, what was the גזירה? gezeirah?
Well because if you're only putting it on the לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat
Parhedrin because you don't want it to make it seem as if
he's חבוש בית אסורים, chavush beit asurim, that to put it on
שער ניקנור Sha'ar Nikanor was going to lead to where the... yeah
I mean you know, which if you will is sort of what
we said on the משנה Mishna about גזירה אחרת אין לה דבר
סוף, gezeira acheret ein la davar sof, right? When put it in
you know one level above it
it goes to אין לה דבר סוף. ein la davar sof.
So, but they said no it's really sort of the same idea
you know in the end. But it's of a you know the
gate closest to לשכת פרהדרין. Lishkat Parhedrin.
This is what we're trying to say now. But
I
don't want to ruin the surprise but you'll see you know should
we why should we have מזוזה mezuzah anywhere you know in קודש?
kodesh? And we'll get to that on the יום ב. yom bet.
So if you have a lot of questions you know think of
that because you know because they'll all be probably relevant to what
we're going to be learning today. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan ובשעריך uvisharecha
על מזוזות ביתך
ובשעריך.
al mezuzot beitecha
uvisharecha. So אחד שערי בתים echad sha'arei batim and so the if
you will the gates to your house maybe door but
as
opposed to חצרות chatzerot right? So
a חצר chatzer would be your courtyard. So you know just think
of you know multiple access points basically.
So אחד שערי בתים ואחד שערי חצרות ואחד שערי מדינות. echad sha'arei
batim ve'echad sha'arei chatzerot ve'echad sha'arei medinot. Even gates to the country.
You know I guess now we have sort of like borders that
are a little bit they've taken down some of these borders but
you know perhaps there was some sort of I don't know what
there would have been. I don't know how you see unless it's
the Great Wall of China but
how about ceremonial
arches
that mark the Delaware Pennsylvania line? That kind of thing.
Hadrian's Wall in Scotland.
But anyway so were it to have some sort of I'm going
to talk about archways in particular actually later but but
just
for now just for ease just you know assume like these like
nice big square gates right? So ואחד שערי עיירות ve'echad sha'arei ayarot
city gates יש בהן חובת מצווה למקום. yesh bahen chovat mitzvah lamakom.
Very interesting way of saying it right? יש בהן חובת מצווה למקום.
yesh bahen chovat mitzvah lamakom. Like you don't really see that kind
of language too often. יש בהן חובת מצווה למקום. yesh bahen chovat
mitzvah lamakom. Like you know the obligation of the מצווה mitzvah for
השם. Hashem. משום שנאמר וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך ובשעריך. mishum shene'emar uchtavtam
al mezuzot beitecha uvisharecha. So didn't say which שערים sha'arim right? So
so include them all. So actually
I printed out something over here that says that it's a very
you know unusually elaborate expression over here. Why not just say that
it's just you know חייב במזוזה chayav bemezuzah right? What's יש בהן
חובת מצווה למקום? yesh bahen chovat mitzvah lamakom? So שיח יצחק Siach
Yitzchak says that this is where you get into these these other
notions in מזוזה mezuzah
and in the גמרא עבודה זרה Gemara Avodah Zarah actually talks about
the whole
talks about an incident with אונקלוס. Onkelos. So like how he became
a גר ger and then and then the government tried to like
send all these people you know then he always had these conversations
with them and everything he said you know caused whoever it is
that came to try to you know I guess maybe bring him
for interrogation whatever it is to convert right? So it happened like
three or four times and you know then the officials eventually gave
up. Like he's just he's not worth it you know we're never
we're not going to succeed. Anyway so one of the things he
said is you know look look at you know he tried to
compare
people to השם Hashem you know and how his מידה midah is
much better. So anyway so what arises from there
is that basically you know there's this idea of like a מזוזה
mezuzah like you know watch protection right? Which is then you know
makes it a little bit difficult because then you know becomes some
sort of talisman but anyway but but the point is that there
is an idea of protection.
So and also גמרא Gemara later which says that מזוזה mezuzah brings
long life and
which is why perhaps even a rented maybe a reason why a
rented home would require מזוזה mezuzah which is a whole other conversation
we'll get to that too. But anyway so the point is so
then you might have thought that okay well if it's the idea
of protection then
well if we all have our houses and all of our houses
have מזוזות mezuzot. then we're good right? What's the point of having
it on your שערים? sha'arim? So so therefore
it is it is true that you don't need it for the
sake of protection potentially although you know there's differences between protecting you
as a family level as opposed to you in a national level
but nevertheless so even though it's not for the idea of protection
you still need it because there's השם's Hashem מצווה mitzvah so to
speak. I mean maybe that's why it says it like that. I
don't know take that take that or leave it but anyway the
point being
ובשעריך is more expansive and includes all these other שערים. sha'arim. Okay.
אמר
ליה אביי לרב ספרא Amar leh Abaye leRav Safra הני אבולי דמחוזא.
hani avulei deMechuza. מחוזא Mechuza is a place
and how they're translating אבולי avulei exactly? Like שערי עיר.
sha'arei ir.
Okay so that's what רש"י Rashi says שערי העיר ששמה מחוזא. sha'arei
ha'ir she'shma Mechuza. So I guess אבולי avulei is is yeah we'll
go with that. So the the gates of
מחוזא Mechuza מאי טעמא לא עבדו להו רבנן מזוזה? mai ta'ama lo
avdu lehu rabanan mezuzah?
Okay,
so why don't they have a
מזוזה? mezuzah? So אמר להו חזוק דאקרא
וקוביהו דעבידי.
amar lehu chizuk d'akra
v'kubeyhu d'avidai.
So
basically
now we're dealing with the types of structures. So basically, you know,
what they're trying to say is that it was constructed almost as
like a fort, right? As opposed to like a some sort of
habitat, almost habitable or throughway. This was just, you know, I guess
what they're saying is what he's trying to answer is some sort
of architectural, you know, flourish of some sort that really wasn't, you
know, just not as functional
in the typical way that the שערים shearim would be. So he
says, אמר ליה סוף סוף ואקרא דקובי גופא לא בעי מזוזה והתניא
רבי יהודה אומר בית האסורין? amar lei sof sof v'akra d'kuvei gufah
lo ba'ei mezuzah v'ha'tanya Rabbi Yehuda omer beit ha'asurin? So okay, so
what? I mean, like, you know, at the end of the day,
like, you know, we had we had this before, like if you
have when we even introduced this at some point that if you
have a בית דירה beit dira in there, right, then the then
what leads up to it would still require a מזוזה. mezuzah. So
at the end of the day, you know, there is some sort
of
habitation, you know, a room, an area over there that does have
the city watch person, right? So this is what's leading up to
it. So it should have a מזוזה mezuzah anyway.
Regardless of, you know, you're saying okay, it's more it's more like
support, but still at the end of the day, you know, there
is a function within these שערים. shearim. And והתניא בית הכנסת שיש
בו בית דירה לחזן הכנסת. v'ha'tanya beit haknesset sheyesh bo beit dira
l'chazzan haknesset.
So if there's a בית הכנסת beit haknesset and if it has,
you know, call it an apartment for the sexton, the חזן chazzan
of the of the area, the caretaker, חייבת במזוזה. chayevet b'mezuzah.
So this should be no different. אלא אמר אביי משום סכנה. Ella
amar Abaye mishum sakana. Oh no, this is a little bit different
because סכנה. sakana. So basically, and we'll read this story and I'll
have to explain it to you. דתניא מזוזת יחיד נבדקת פעמיים בשבוע
ושל רבים פעמיים ביובל.
De'tanya mezuzat yachid nivdeket pa'amayim b'shavua v'shel
rabbim pa'amayim b'yovel. So
our our own מזוזות mezuzot in our homes have to be checked
twice בשבוע. b'shavua. They don't mean twice a week, but בשבוע b'shavua
as in like a, you know, שמיטה shmita cycle. So twice twice
in that cycle. ושל רבים פעמיים ביובל. V'shel rabbim pa'amayim b'yovel. But
if it's a public one, then you get a much much longer
time frame and you only have to do it twice in a
יובל. yovel. יובל Yovel being basically a 50-year period. And I'll circle
back to this. I just want to read the answer. ואמר רבי
יהודה מעשה V'amar Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh and this is why we're quoting
this, ואמר רבי יהודה מעשה בארטבין אחד שהיה בודק מזוזות בשוק העליון
של צפורי. v'amar Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh b'Artavin echad shehayah bodek mezuzot be'shuk
ha'elyon shel Tzipori. So this one this one guy, how do you
exactly translate ארטבין? Artavin? It could be like
his profession or the guy was or somehow his his name.
Whatever it is, so this guy was checking the מזוזות mezuzot in
the שוק העליון של צפורי, shuk ha'elyon shel Tzipori, the upper marketplace.
מצאו קוסטור אחד. Matzo kastor echad. So one of these like officials
of the government found him. ונטל ממנו אלף זוז. V'natal mimenu elef
zuz. Took
from him a thousand זוז. zuz. And that's how it ends. So
like what are we trying to prove right there? But the point
is that it's a סכנה. sakana. Why is and and we
adduce proof to that from the אלף זוז elef zuz but what's
being read in here is the reason why a thousand זוז zuz
fine or they took from him because it was as if he
was doing some sort of incantation witchcraft. If he's doing, you know,
casting a hex on our gate. So the point being is it's
very public, as opposed to your house, you know, you can do
whatever you need to in your house, no one's going to think
you're, you know, no one's really looking so much about that, but
as opposed to the public access points, it's a bit more dangerous
to be doing like these strange things, right? So anyway, so the
point is that therefore you don't need to check it as much.
So or and in this case, I guess, since it was such
a public place and, you know, maybe given the fact that maybe
it was a Babylonian city, they thought, you know, what are these
people doing here putting מזוזות mezuzot there, you know, then
what is that thing they're putting there, you know? So that's a
little bit too difficult.
A certain tension between the like what is the obligation if it's
a majority Jewish city but not under Jewish dominion. Right.
Well, apparently this was and even although the dominion is clearly exercised
by the non-Jewish government.
Mm-hmm. And there have been cities like that within the past century.
Salonika. Salonika. ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Not sure if that had gates, though.
Salonika was a walled city.
Oh yeah? Until a great fire. It had a fire that decimated
the city in the early 20th century.
Wonder if it had מזוזות?
mezuzot For the most part, the Jewish quarter before that happened.
Okay, so I'll discuss just for a few moments about the twice
seven years or twice a יובל. yovel. So anyway, you can ask
if it doesn't say once every three and a half... Oh yeah?
Until a great fire. It had a fire that decimated the city
in the early 20th century. Destroyed most of the Jewish quarter. But
before that happened... Okay, so I'll discuss just for a few moments
about the twice seven years or twice יובל. Yovel. So anyway, you
can ask if it doesn't say once every three and a half
years, right? And it doesn't. So if you want to do a
רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, then it means okay, so twice יובל. Yovel.
I'll do it year one, year two, and then wait for another
five years, right? And what's the difference? That means we, so the
גמרא Gemara seems to have said a difference, again public, it may
look a little bit whatever more strange and you don't want to
get into trouble. Anyway, so,
the point is that according, according to רש"י, Rashi,
he says נבדקת Nivdeket שמא נרקבה או נגנבה, Shema nirkava o nignava,
right? Why bother checking it at all? Because perhaps it rotted,
meaning like a piece of paper so at some point it may
have just deteriorated due to exposure to the elements of some sort
or נגנבה, nignava, you want to check it's even there. Not paper.
Not paper, I mean קלף, klaf, I meant to say like some
biodegradable substance, how about that?
How do you translate פעמיים בשבוע? paamayim bashavua?
Well that's what, פעמיים בשבוע paamayim bashavua twice in a, in a
שמיטה shmita cycle.
Right, twice in every seven.
Right. So what I'm trying to say is like, could it mean
you do it today and then tomorrow, then wait another? I guess
I'll get back in a second. So,
anyway so that's what, that's what רש"י Rashi says. Interestingly enough, though
I will point out that that's in contrast to תפילין, tefillin, which
are if they're worn regularly they don't actually need to be checked
at all מצד ההלכה. mitzad ha'halacha. So, it's only if you haven't
worn them in quite a while that then you should start checking
them. Maybe we should check, we should, I mean we do,
I'm not saying this as a proscription, but I think it's pretty
common for people to check their תפילין tefillin anyway at some point.
You asked how often.
What exactly are you checking them for?
To see if like, well, for, do all the, does any of
the letters deteriorate? Is what's written still...
But if you wear it regularly, you would imagine you'd have to
check it more often.
You think so, right? Yeah. But,
but according, but
then again, perhaps at least certainly according to the נגנבה, nignava, right?
You're wearing your תפילין, tefillin, you know it's not stolen. So, as
opposed to the מזוזה, mezuzah, you may not notice, especially if it's
hollowed into like one of these things, into the actual structure of
the wall.
I thought that if it's worn, it's like
if you find it, תפילין tefillin somewhere, like you're going through the
basement of a שול shul and you find some תפילין tefillin and
probably nobody's worn them in decades.
Right, well, that. Or
right, or like let's say you inherited the תפילין tefillin from whoever
it was, right, and the person, or maybe you had two pairs
of תפילין, tefillin, you didn't really wear this one, it was a
backup, right? Or you inherited it and
then you want to give it to your kid or something and
they haven't been used for however long, then you should, you should
check it. That's תפילין. tefillin. So מזוזה mezuzah anyway according to רש"י,
Rashi, maybe it rotted away or maybe it got stolen. תוספות ישנים
Tosafot Yeshanim
says
that the reason why רבנן Rabbanan enact, so again as implied by
our גמרא, Gemara, so for מזוזת השערים, mezuzat hashearim, so it's dangerous,
the inspectors faced due to these, either decrees issued by the foreign
government against
fulfilling מצוות, mitzvot, makes it harder to check public one. Or you
can say, what we just said a moment ago, that forget about
against מצוות, mitzvot, they're just gonna suspect you of something improper.
You can't win with this. If the גמרא Gemara said once in
three and a half years, then you would have asked in the
morning or in the afternoon? Right? It's true. Since it says
twice in seven years, you say well it could be today and
tomorrow and then not for seven years. What are you gonna do?
But others say that the reason why מזוזות mezuzot? in the public
area
are investigated less frequently is because if so many people are passing
by, they're essentially watching them more often. So, they don't need to
check it as much, less likely to be stolen or you may
say it's more likely to be stolen. I don't know, but that's
what somebody says.
Mezuzot are often marked or hidden though? Yeah,
it doesn't make sense.
I know, it's really, that's why you have so many answers. So,
anyway so the point is though that
as opposed to,
so רב חיים קניבסקי Rav Chaim Kanievsky says that you can't really
get by by doing it, once and then right away again. Although
we're saying twice in seven years, it really means once every three
and a half years. So, you can't get out of, you can't
like try to do some sort of like hop and skip. Four
days in a row? Yeah, exactly.
And how often would you check a תורה, Torah, ספר תורה? Sefer
Torah?
Only you don't need to check it at all unless you have,
as far as I understand it, three
פסולים psulim on like one column.
Then you have to check it.
Then you have to check the whole thing. But even if you
have one, so you just correct it, right?
But I mean some people,
if you find one they check the whole thing, or others, even
right after it's written, you can put it through a whole software
that scans the thing, but as far as I understand, you don't
actually have to do that. Okay, so
that's about the שערים shearim in the house.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask the question
that, so this remember this inspector who got fined a thousand זוז?
zuz? So אמר ליה... Amar lei... אמר רב אלעזר שלוחי מצווה אינם
ניזוקים. amar rav elazar shluchei mitzvah einam nizokim. How could it let
it happen? He's doing a מצווה, mitzvah, you know, how can anything
bad happen to him? So the גמרא Gemara gives an answer that's
given often enough when these this
issue
arose. So and and if you will most poignantly when we talked
about the the idea of אחר, Acher, right? So we saw you
know one of the things that he saw was the guy the
the boy going up the ladder and you know got killed, isn't
he שלוחי מצווה? shluchei mitzvah? So the answer is היכא דשכיח היזיקא
שאני heicha dishchiach heizeika shani when there's a היזיקא heizeik it's different
and you know the answer that they gave over there was that
the boy was going up like a rickety ladder so you know
despite the promises of a of a long life you know if
he's putting himself in a this in a potentially you know
unstable situation then bad things may happen. So and how do we
know that if there's a potential for היזיקא heizeik that you won't
necessarily be protected even if you're doing a מצווה? mitzvah? Because דכתיב
ויאמר שמואל איך אלך ושמע שאול והרגני. dichtiv vayomer shmuel eich eileich
v'shama shaul v'haragani. So
שמואל Shmuel was was
tasked with anointing דוד David and he's saying well how am I
going to possibly do that? There's an existing king over there and
if שאול Shaul hears about this he will kill me. So
and what does השם Hashem say? השם Hashem says what are you
doing you of little faith you know you're going on a מצווה
mitzvah of my command? No. השם Hashem says ויאמר השם עגלת בקר
קח בידך ואמרת לזבוח להשם באתי. vayomer hashem eglyat bakar kach b'yadecha
v'amarta lizboach l'hashem bati. A ruse, right? You know you gotta do
some things you know to deflect suspicion so take you know this
this
calf and say oh yeah you know I'm doing some sort of
ritual you know just say that right? So which means you know
there's a potential to be ניזוק nizzok you gotta take precautions don't
don't rely on the fact that you're doing a מצווה. mitzvah. Okay,
תני רב כהנה קמיה דרב יהודה tanni rav kahana kamei d'rav yehuda
בית התבן. beit hateven. Now what houses? בביתך ובשעריך. b'vatecha u'v'shareicha. So
is it בית התבן beit hateven which is like a storehouse you
know for wheat, בית הבקר beit habakar a barn, בית העצים. beit
ha'etzim. I have to tell you you know so far so good
but it's going to be very weird. ובית העצים u'veit ha'etzim a
house where you store wood, ובית האוצרות u'veit ha'otzarot some sort of
general storehouse maybe for oil, פטורים מן המזוזה. p'turim min hamazuza. Okay
but what's the reason? מפני mipnei shehanashim ניאותות ne'otot bahen because the
women are ניאותות ne'otot bahen. What does that mean? מאי ניאותות mai
ne'otot רוחצות. rokhtzot. They wash in them. Now I don't really understand
that. I mean I'm hoping most women aren't really washing in barns.
I really didn't get it.
I mean but why would they not need a מזוזה? mazuza?
Well he says oh no we'll get to that but but
because הנשים רוחצות hanashim rokhtzot and then what so so the גמרא
Gemara doesn't actually explain this but they say look at רש"י. Rashi.
ניאותות ne'otot רוחצות rokhtzot ניאותות לשון הנאה ne'otot lashon hana'ah ומשום דמקום
גנאי
הוא.
u'mishum d'makom
gnai hu. I mean
in רש"י Rashi משום דשם ערומות אין כבוד שמים להיות שם מזוזה.
mishum d'sham arumot ein kavod shamayim l'hiyot sham mazuza. So because people
how about the
wet places where men get
oh perfect perfect right no we'll get to all this. So because
you know because people are unclothed women specifically are unclothed. But again
I don't I just maybe
it
was just a
place where but that's the funny thing I mean you'd think that
these places will be פטור patur because they're not מקום דירה. makom
dira.
Right no I know we'll get to that. I mean remember I
told you the גמרא's Gemara going to like you know get to
a whole bunch of different but you're right I mean we're going
to get to as much there and it's just very very odd.
So
I mean if you want to look at תוספות Tosafot he says
אף על פי ש... af al pi she... oh no no we'll
get that's that's the next one. I'll hold I'll hold off for
a moment. So anyway so
I so
תוספות Tosafot anyway tries to say that
that well it really depends what kind of בית הבקר beit habakar
you know
because
if like you know there's really going to be animals there that
you know like I mean you know there's going to be all
sorts of not nice things in there do you think people are
really taking their baths there? No. So it depends you know it
may not be it may not be a בית הבקר beit habakar
that people you know really put in animals all the time בקביעות.
b'kevi'ut. But anyway but the point is maybe it was water kept
there.
Yeah that's that's
what I was thinking in a בית הבקר.
beit habakar. Yeah. Oh okay maybe right.
So anyways this this could has to be something that potentially you
know within the realm of somebody wanting to bathe in there.
Okay anyway so anyway the point being is because right? It doesn't
say any place הנשים רוחצות hanashim rokhtzot right? It says all this
is because of הנשים רוחצות hanashim rokhtzot then you don't have a
מזוזה. mazuza. אמר רב יהודה תני רוחצות amar rav yehuda tanni rokhtzot
which implies okay because they they
wash. והסתמא v'hastama so if they didn't wash הסתמא חייבין hastama chayavin
then they would be obligated. But תני רב פפא tanni r' pappa
בקר פטור מן המזוזה bakar patur min hamazuza so we have another
teaching that it's פטור patur from מזוזה mazuza and they don't say
why but we'll get to all this. אלא מאי ניאותות מתקשטות. ela
mai ne'otot mikashatot. So no ניאותות ne'otot doesn't mean that they wash
so there's no issue of גנאי. gnai. So but the point is
הכי תני אף על פי שהנשים מתקשטות בהן פטורין. hachi tanni af
al pi shehanashim mitkashatot bahen p'turin. So even though women you know
may go in there to adorn themselves it's פטור patur because you're
not really living there so basically potentially like let's say you have
a powder room right you know so you would not need a
מזוזה mazuza for that according to that. So so you can look
at רש"י Rashi אף על פי שהנשים מתקשטות שם ב... af al
pi shehanashim mitkashatot sham b'... בבשמים, b'visamim, סלקא דעתך אמינא salka datach
amina דירה dirah היא, hi, אשמעינן ashmeinan דלאו d'lav דירה dirah היא.
hi. You might have thought, okay, well they're in there, right? So
maybe it's some sort of habitation. No, it's not
really. I guess just getting yourself all perfumed is not enough to
really be considered like
enough דירה. dirah. Now we obviously have to understand what is considered
דירה, dirah, but the point is I guess there's some sort of
threshold and this didn't meet it.
You want to say something? Okay. אמר ליה Amar leih רב כהנא:
Rav Kahana: בית שנשים מתקשטות בהן פטורין. beit shenashim mitkashtot bahen peturin.
So you're trying to say that it's נשים מתקשטות בהן nashim mitkashtot
bahen and even then it's פטור, patur, אבל הא תניא aval ha
tanya רפת בקר פטורה מן המזוזה, refet bakar peturah min hamizuzah, this
stable barn whatever is פטור patur from a
מזוזה, mezuzah, ובית שנשים מתקשטות בהן חייבת במזוזה, v'beit shenashim mitkashtot bahen
chayavet bimzuza, but if נשים nashim are מתקשטות mitkashtot it is חייב
במזוזה chayav b'mzuza because that is considered enough of a דירה. dirah.
So אלא מאי אית לך למימר? ela mai it lach l'meimar? So
what can you say? I mean look, we have רפת בקר refet
bakar פטור, patur, רפת בקר refet bakar חייב, chayav נשים מתקשטות בהן
nashim mitkashtot bahen potentially
פטור, patur, נשים מתקשטות בהן nashim mitkashtot bahen חייב. chayav, How do
you make sense of all this? תנאי Tannai היא, hi, it's a
מחלוקת. machloket.
דידי נמי סתמא תנאי היא. didi nami stamah Tannai hi. So both
these things are מחלוקת. machloket. So for me too I can say
there's a
מחלוקת. machloket. דתניא: D'tanya: ביתך, Beitcha. זו ביתך ובשעריך. zu beitcha u'vish'arecha.
ביתך. beitcha. So ביתך. What does that mean? ביתך המיוחד לך. Beitcha
hamiyuchad lach. It's like real for people, right? People places. פרט לבית
התבן ולבית הבקר ולבית העצים ולבית האוצרות שפטורים מן המזוזה. Perat l'veit
hateven u'l'veit habakar u'l'veit haetzim u'l'veit haotzarot shepeturin min hamizuzah.
So it exempts all these other places we talked about, not because
נשים nashim are מתקשטות mitkashtot or נאותות ne'otot or whatever it is
you want to explain it, but because it's just not considered a
house. It's a storehouse, the wheat house, all these places are פטור
patur from a מזוזה. mezuzah. ויש מחייבין. V'yesh mechayvin. But nevertheless there's
those that say you're חייב. chayav. באמת אמרו בית הכסא, B'emet amru
beit hakisei, right? So talking about like places of טינוף tinuf or
people being naked or somewhat unclothed anyway, בית הכסא beit hakisei would
be a perfect example, right? So בין רואים בין נראים bein ro'im
bein nira'im whatever, right? בית הכסא ובית הבורסקי ובית המרחץ ובית הטבילה,
Beit hakisei u'veit habursaki u'veit hamerchatz u'veit hatevilah, right? That's בית המרחץ,
beit hamerchatz, bathhouse,
ובית הטבילה u'veit hatevilah where you go to the מקוה. mikvah. I
guess
men or women, but ושנשים נאותות בהן. v'shenashim ne'otot bahen. And now
this separates it. ושנשים נאותות בהן. v'shenashim ne'otot bahen. Or places that
נשים nashim are נאותות. ne'otot. Salon. Oh interesting. Yeah. פטורים מן המזוזה.
peturin min hamizuzah.
So okay, so obviously this is a matter of debate, right? Because
you see like a yes, no, yes, no, right? רב כהנא מתריץ
לטעמיה ורב יהודה מתריץ לטעמיה. Rav Kahana matritz l'taameih v'Rav Yehuda matritz
l'taameih. So רב כהנא מתריץ לטעמיה. Rav Kahana matritz l'taameih. ביתך המיוחד
לך. Beitcha hamiyuchad lach.
So he says that it's your house, the one that
is like for people. פרט לבית התבן ובית הבקר ובית העצים ובית
האוצרות פטורין
מן המזוזה.
perat l'veit hateven u'veit habakar u'veit
haetzim u'veit haotzarot peturin min hamizuzah. בסתם, b'stam, right? That so
סתם, stam, but ויש מחייבין בסתם. v'yesh mechayvin b'stam. But those that
say no, you still have to. ובאמת אמרו בית הכסא u'vemet amru
beit hakisei and these other things, ובית הבורסקי ובית המרחץ ובית הטבילה
ושנשים נאותות בהן. u'veit habursaki u'veit hamerchatz u'veit hatevilah v'shenashim ne'otot bahen.
All these places and then מאי נאותות בהן? mai ne'otot bahen? רוחצות.
rochatzot. פטורין מן המזוזה. Peturin min hamizuzah. But the problem with that
is if you're saying נאותות ne'otot is רוחצות, rochatzot, then היינו מרחץ,
hainu merchatz, right? We said one along this whole list was a
מרחץ. merchatz. So why are you saying a place where there's a
מרחץ merchatz and where נשים nashim are נאותות, ne'otot, which is a
מרחץ? merchatz? You're just repeating yourself. Right? You get that? Because in
our list was מרחץ merchatz and a place that נשים נאותות. nashim
ne'otot. And if you're saying נאותות ne'otot is מרחץ, merchatz, then you've
just said the same thing twice. So נאותות ne'otot should be something
different than מרחץ.
merchatz. I actually had a question about that.
In this context of antiquity, was the מרחץ merchatz
only
for men, only were they separate, were they mixed, like the general
מרחץ? merchatz? I think they were definitely separate. I think no, Hellenistic
מרחץ, merchatz, the women go to a מרחץ. merchatz.
It's a good question. You always hear about the men going, right?
Yeah, in other words the מרחץ merchatz was deeply embedded in Hellenistic
culture and in the entire entire area there's always a מרחץ. merchatz.
I don't know the question did women use a מרחץ? merchatz?
Isn't there a story that somebody's mother conceived him in a מרחץ?
merchatz?
There is she went into the water, the semen was in the
water.
So that's she had אריסא. Arisa. Like were the Hellenistic מרחצאות merchatzaot
mixed? I don't know, I don't know anything.
I can't imagine the Greeks would have tolerated women in their bathhouse.
Or Pompeii which is like at the same time.
Yeah. Okay. In other words the reason why I'm asking is so
that in other words the place where the women bathed and the
place where the men bathed were two different
places.
Yeah, okay.
ובית נאותות v'veit ne'otot and מרחץ merchatz is just I don't know.
But
the גמרא. Gemara. So
anyway, I'm gonna move on. But the ונהי דהכי. u'nehi d'hachi. So
what's the difference? So אשמעינן מרחץ דרבים ashmina merchatz d'rabbim ואשמעינן מרחץ
דיחיד. ve'ashmina merchatz d'yachid.
So there's public and then there's like private. So let's say you
have a private מרחץ. merchatz. You say you actually had indoor plumbing
of somehow, you know, so that'd be... Yeah, you know, especially for
nobility, might have that.
According to the internet, Republican bathhouses often had separate bathing facilities for
women and men. But by the empire, the custom was to open
the bathhouses to women during the early part of the day and
reserve it for men from 2:00 PM until closing.
Oh, separate swimming. Yeah.
That's Roman. Yeah, which would have been at least in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael.
Okay, anyway, so you need מרחץ דרבים merchatz d'rabbim and you need
מרחץ דיחיד. merchatz d'yachid. סלקא דעתך אמינא מרחץ דרבים דנפיש זוהמא, Salkah
da'atach amina merchatz d'rabbim d'nafish zu'ama, right, because there's a lot of
dirt. More people equals more dirt I guess, so that makes it
less מכובד. mechubad. אבל מרחץ דיחיד דלא נפיש זוהמא, Aval merchatz d'yachid
d'lo nafish zu'ama, just one person, you know, how disgusting will it
get, אימא לא ליחייב במזוזה קא משמע לן, eima lo l'chayeiv be'mezuzah
kama shma lan, no, it's just, you know,
inappropriate. Right? So okay, ורב יהודה מתרץ לטעמיה הכי קתני בית התבן
בית הבקר בית העצים ובית האוצרות פטורים מן המזוזה. ve'Rav Yehuda mitarais
l'ta'amei hachi katani beis hatieven beis habakar beis ha'etzim ve'beis ha'otzaros p'turim
min hamazuzah. Same thing,
even מתקשטות, mitkashtos, because remember we had the idea of what נאותות
ne'otot is. Is it מתקשטות mitkashtos or is it רוחצות? rochatzos? That
was the point of contention between the two, right? So רב כהנא
Rav Kahana just explained it his way that it really is מרחץ,
merchatz, right?
And so he says and but רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda saying, is
it from מתקשטות mitkashtos to signify that you're preparing yourself, ויש חייבין
במתקשטות. ve'yesh chayavin be'mitkashtos. And those that again, you have to say
it's a מחלוקת תנאים machloket tana'im because you've just so many contradictions,
but just a matter of how you explain some of these specifics.
Again, everyone agrees that בית אוצר בית התבן בית beis ha'otzar beis
hatieven beis whatever it is are all exempt, but then when you
deal with this מרחצות, merchatzot, I mean נאותות, ne'otot, you have to
explain what that means, right? So one explains it as רוחצות rochatzos
in which case then how do you deal with the... let me
just get through this one then... in which case then how do
you get through the repetitions? Okay, so different types, public versus private.
So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda would say, you know, two separate things,
right? It's not מרחץ merchatz and מרחץ, merchatz, rather it's מרחץ merchatz
and מתקשטות. mitkashtos. So ויש חייבין במתקשטות אבל סתם דברי הכל פטור
ובאמת אמרו בית הכסא בית הבורסקי בית המרחץ ובית הטבילה אף על
פי שנשים מתקשטות בהן פטורים מן המזוזה משום דנפיש זוהמא.
ve'yesh chayavin be'mitkashtos aval stam divrei hakol patur ve'emet amru beis hakisei
beis habursaki beis hamerchatz ve'beis hatevilah af al pi shenashim mitkashtot bahen
p'turim
min hamazuzah mishum d'nafish zu'ama.
So now you know, so now why are the other ones בית
הכסא בית הבורסקי beis hakisei beis habursaki all these other places and
בית המרחץ, beis hamerchatz, and again בית המרחץ beis hamerchatz is not
repeated because first was מתקשטות mitkashtot and now this is a place
where they're actually washing, you know, so people are undressed or there's
an element of dirt there.
So these places are פטורים מן המזוזה
משום דנפיש זוהמא. p'turim min hamazuzah mishum d'nafish zu'ama.
Okay, your question was?
Just, you know, this whole סוגיא's sugya structure is held together by
this phrase ובאמת אמרו. be'emet amru. Yeah. So I just, I don't
know if ובאמת אמרו be'emet amru is like a הכי קאמר hachi
ka'amar or a חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני chisura mechsra vehachi katani or
if it's just a literary way of saying I'm going to reword
it so I can give a new explanation as to why, a
new
טעם, ta'am, משום דנפיש זוהמא.
mishum d'nafish zu'ama. Like after every ובאמת אמרו be'emet amru there's like
a טעם ta'am which is like different, so maybe it was the
Talmud's way of reorganizing the sources to try to clarify a consistent
explanation that will make everything fit together.
If I remember correctly, and this is
a bigger if, we actually have sometimes these things like, you know,
also by רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon ובאמת אמרו be'emet amru even in
משניות, mishnayos, and I think what we had commented on there is
like, you know, that may be like an older משנה, mishna, right,
which has been since been expanded upon, or that really is
a הלכה, halacha, and it may have some potentially contradictory evidence, but
the real הלכה halacha is ובאמת אמרו. be'emet amru. It really underscores
that that's like really the הלכה. halacha.
Yeah, no, but it's like doing something technical. Like what you just
said, like we've got these ברייתות, braitos, we've got these משניות, mishnayos,
but והלכתא... ve'hilcheta... Right.
And then it has some
rhetorical function.
The whole thing is
strung on these ובאמת אמרו. be'emet amru.
But maybe it's that the הלכה halacha is clear, but ובאמת אמרו
be'emet amru is a reflection on reality. What do people, how do
people actually use bathhouses, tanneries, and so on?
But I think ובאמת אמרו be'emet amru is more of an הלכתי
halachic function as opposed to like, you know, the מציאות metzius of
it.
You know what I mean?
ובאמת אמרו be'emet amru always
ends with a הלכה halacha here, and a טעם. ta'am.
No, that's what I'm saying. The reason, because the real nature... everybody
knows the הלכה halacha is basically בית דירה beis dira or not,
right? That's, I mean, that's clear through this whole discussion. ובאמת אמרו
be'emet amru is, well, what about this tannery? What about this bathhouse?
And the reason that ובאמת אמרו, be'emet amru, that the real nature
of the bathhouse is such and such, therefore yes or no.
I'm just pointing out, you know, just striking as you were leading,
that the whole structure of the whole thing is just like a
link between all these pieces.
Okay, so
yes, okay. Now if
you, no no no, I just want to get my sources here.
So if you remember what precipitated this whole conversation,
it was, remember we had the whole thing about רחצות Ruchatzot versus
not? And they said רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda I'm going up on
top. You don't have to go there. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
had said what do you mean רחצות Ruchatzot which means סתם חייבין?
stam chayavin? You know מסתמא mistama if they weren't, they'd be חייב?
chayav. No, I don't think so and then this launches this whole
conversation. So the point was רבי יהודה סתמא דבי כל פטור, Rabbi
Yehuda stama d'vei kol patur, right? If it's סתם stam then would
you be פטור? patur? דתני בשעריך אחד שערי בתים ואחד שערי חצרות
ואחד שערי מדינות ואחד שערי עיירות ורפת
ולולין, d'tana bish'arecha echad sha'arei batim v'echad sha'arei chatzerot v'echad sha'arei medinot
v'echad sha'arei ayarot v'refet v'lulin, the stable and like a chicken coop,
ומתבן u'matben is
some תבן, teven, ואוצרות יין ואוצרות שמן חייבין במזוזה, v'otzarot yayin v'otzarot
shemen chayavin bimzuza, right?
So now we're saying that they're
חייב. chayav? יכול שאני מרבה אף בית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת? Yachol she'ani
merbeh af beit sha'ar achsadra u'mirpeset? So what about a בית שער
beit sha'ar that as רש"י Rashi explains is like a little house
that you do before the שער sha'ar and the חצר chatzer and
it's just a passageway or a מרפסת, mirpeset, like a balcony?
תלמוד לומר בית מה בית מיוחד לדירה יצאו אלו שאין מיוחדין לדירה.
Talmud lomar bayit,
mah bayit meyuchad l'dirah yatztzu elu she'ein meyuchadin l'dirah.
So it says בית. bayit. Oh, just like a בית bayit is
מיוחד לדירה, meyuchad l'dirah, these are not.
יכול שאני מרבה אף בית הכסא? Yachol she'ani merbeh af beit hakise?
People, I mean people are in the בית הכסא. beit hakise. Is
it sarcastic? What? You'll see but I'll point out a glaring problem
but in a minute but יכול yachol after I read this I'll
pause for a second and I'll ask you what you think the
problem is. יכול שאני מרבה אף בית הכסא ובית הבורסקי ובית המרחץ
ובית התפילה? Yachol she'ani merbeh af beit hakise u'veit haburski u'veit hamerchatz
u'veit hatefillah? Okay well look people are there, I mean they may
not be doing something you like but they're there.
תלמוד לומר בית מה בית עשוי לכבוד אף כל עשוי לכבוד יצאו
אלו שאין עשויין לכבוד.
Talmud lomar bayit mah bayit asui l'chavod af kol asui l'chavod yatztzu
elu she'ein asuyin
l'chavod.
I'll stop here for a minute but what's the problem with what
I just read? And I'll even it's the very it's the first
three lines.
That בית bayit is in the is in the name. Yeah but
this little piece
of the סוגיא sugya didn't you know with what we had just
spent the last 20 minutes reading?
So בית שער, beit sha'ar, right? We said oh it's a בית
קטן שעושים לפני השער חצר bayit katan she'osim lifnei hasha'ar chatzer but
what do you mean? Didn't we have the thing that you know
that the people go through this is a בית דירה beit dirah
then he needs one? So what do you mean you're saying you
wouldn't do it?
I don't understand the question.
No here we're saying he says יכול שאני מרבה אף בית שער
בית אכסדרה מרפסת, yachol she'ani merbeh af beit sha'ar beit achsadra mirpeset,
right? That maybe it may need a מזוזה. mezuzah. No, it doesn't.
But what do you mean? Didn't we have that before
about
that you know we have this בית שער beit sha'ar we have
like the we learned elsewhere I mean and even we said as
much almost over here that if the בית הכנסת... beit haknesset...
if it has a בית דירה לשומר beit dirah l'shomer then even
like the passageway would need it, right? But I was also remembering
and the תוספות Tosfot asks this. I'll if you want to look
at it it's י"א ע"א. yud aleph amud aleph. יכול שאני מרבה
אף בית שער וכולי. Yachol she'ani merbeh af beit sha'ar v'chulu. משמע
דבית שער פטור ממזוזה. Mashma d'veit sha'ar patur mimzuza. ותימא דפרק הקומץ
רבה במנחות V'teima d'perek ha-kometz rabba b'menachot which is where this another
main aspect of this is which I wanted to bring there. תני
בית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת חייבת במזוזה, Tana beit sha'ar achsadra u'mirpeset chayavet
bimzuza, right? You know we have exact opposite teaching in מנחות Menachot
that these בית שער beit sha'ar and אכסדרה achsadra is חייב ממזוזה.
chayav mimzuza. Here he just said a second ago it's פטור ממזוזה.
patur mimzuza. So which is it? וכן משמע בפרק קמא דסוכה דבית
שער חייב במזוזה. V'chen mashma b'perek kama d'Sukkah d'veit sha'ar chayav b'mzuza.
So his answer יש לומר דהכא מדאורייתא קאמר והתם מדרבנן. yesh lomar
d'hacha mid'oraita k'amar v'hata mid'rabbanan. So depends if you're talking מדאורייתא mid'oraita
or מדרבנן. mid'rabbanan. So מדרבנן mid'rabbanan you're חייב, chayav. מדאורייתא mid'oraita you're
פטור. patur. אינמי נראה לי דהכא מיירי בבית שער של אכסדרה או
בית שער של
מרפסת והא דקתני בית שער אכסדרה פירוש של אכסדרה.
Inami nireh li d'hacha mairay b'veit sha'ar shel achsadra o
beit sha'ar shel mirpeset v'ha d'ktani beit sha'ar achsadra perush shel achsadra.
Anyway the point is look at the last three lines. תרץ התם
דפתוחין לבית. Teretz hatam d'pituachin labayit. So now's now's a very big
difference. So if you have a בית שער beit sha'ar but it's
going into a בית bayit which basically what we said is before,
right? There's a בית שער beit sha'ar that goes through a דירה,
dirah, right? Then you need a מזוזה. mezuzah. But if it's just
like some sort of decorative thing, right? Of some sort or מרפסת,
mirpeset, right? Which is not really it's not leading into the דירה
dirah let's say it's like you know on your whatever it is
like you know going out to some sort of open air type
of thing then you wouldn't. That's what we're saying here.
So again first answers דאורייתא d'oraita really they all are חייב chayav,
במזוזה bimzuza just like a question of the nature of the obligation
is it דאורייתא. d'oraita. Is it דאורייתא de'orayta or דרבנן? de'rabbanan? The
answer is no. When we say you're, you're חייב מזוזה, chayav mezuzah
that's if it's leading into a בית דירה. beit dirah. And we
say you're not, when we say you're exempt from מזוזה, mezuzah, that's
when it's not leading into a בית דירה. beit dirah. So let's,
and then, and now we can discuss what a בית דירה beit
dirah is, right? Oh, you know, people have to be doing something
מכובד, mechubad, is it a matter of טינוף? tinnuf? All these types
of things, you know, potentially exempt you. But as we saw before,
you know, it's a, it was a debate, right? We had a
תנא tanna who said it is, sometimes it is. So obviously it's
a bit confusing. It's a little bit hard to pin down what
really you need to do. But at the end of the day,
everyone did agree, though, that a בית הכיסא beit hakisei is exempt,
right? The real difference is בית התבן, beit hateven, right? That, yes,
no. Right, that, that was the מחלוקת. machloket. And then potentially this,
this בית שער, beit shaar, you know, may also be a מחלוקת
machloket depending on whether how you view the גמרא gemara מנחות Menachot
which contradicts this one.
Okay, now, okay, יכול שאני מרבה אף הר הבית והלשכות, yachol she-ani
merabeh af Har HaBayit ve-ha-lishkot, just, you know, now coming sort of
full circle. Maybe הר הבית, Har HaBayit, maybe לשכות, lishkot, maybe the
עזרות. azarot. תלמוד לומר בית מה בית שהוא חול אף כל שהוא
חול יצאו אלו שהן קודש.
Talmud lomar 'bayit'. Mah 'bayit' she-hu chol, af kol she-hu
chol, yatze'u elu she-hen kodesh.
So, these are קודש. kodesh. All the other examples that we gave
that are חייב chayav מזוזה mezuzah, are חול. chol. So, which is
why we say that a שול shul doesn't necessarily
need a מזוזה. mezuzah. So, מזוזה mezuzah on a holy place is
now exempt.
So,
okay, תיובתא, tiyufta, right? What? תיובתא, tiyufta, תיובתא. tiyufta. Now we say
תיובתא, tiyufta, what does that have to do with it? Because remember
we said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was challenging רב כהנא. Rav Kahana.
And he said, well what do you mean? I disagree with you.
So רב כהנא'ס Rav Kahana's answer was, no, there's a תנאי, tannai,
מחלוקת תנאי. machloket tannai. So that's תיובתא. tiyufta. Clearly there is מחלוקת
תנאי machloket tannai because we just found so many differences of opinion.
רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, so yes, it's a תיובתא tiyufta to רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda that tried to like say no, you're wrong. That's
what we're saying.
But the problem is with, and now what's the really big problem
with what we just said? Oh, the לשכות, lishkot, יכול שאני מרבה
אף הר הבית והלשכות והעזרות, yachol she-ani merabeh af Har HaBayit ve-ha-lishkot
ve-ha-azarot, they should be חייב chayav in מזוזה. mezuzah. No, it's קודש.
kodesh. What's the huge problem?
The huge problem with that, we just talked about לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat
Parhedrin did have a מזוזה, mezuzah, right? שער ניקנור Shaar Nikanor had
a מזוזה. mezuzah. What do you mean?
You know, it's a גזירה, gezeirah, I mean.
Oh, okay, wait. So, a bunch of answers. So,
one answer is again, is it דאורייתא de'orayta or דרבנן, de'rabbanan, right?
So this ברייתא braita just here that the קודש kodesh doesn't need
it is דאורייתא. de'orayta. But, you know, but as you said,
גזירה, gezeirah, maybe לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin needed it מדרבנן, mi'de'rabbanan, right?
But the רבנן rabbanan didn't agree with that.
Right, exactly. That's, that's, okay. So,
but so the point is that even מדרבנן, mi'de'rabbanan, right, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda says it's exempt. But now the reason why we have
it is a גזירה. gezeirah. So that's even sort of like a
different דרבנן de'rabbanan so to speak, right? So מדאורייתא mi-de'orayta all קודש
kodesh places are exempt.
Now מדרבנן mi-de'rabbanan they sort of have a מחלוקת, machloket, right? And
the רבנן rabbanan say that you need one. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
disagreed with it, says you don't. But nevertheless, everyone agreed that לשכת
פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin had one. Oh, that's a גזירה, gezeirah, you don't
want to say he's חבוש בבית האסורין. chavush b'veit ha'asurin. That's not
even a דרבנן. de'rabbanan. That's like a מראית עין marit ayin kind
of thing, right? So it's not like
your extra מדרבנן, mi-de'rabbanan, right? It's a one-case exception. So that's the
one answer.
So another answer I'm actually going to deal with more tomorrow because
this answer will be like completely left field. So anyway, המאירי ha-Meiri
says that, ah, well, what do we mean by קודש, kodesh, right?
קודש, kodesh, is that a location or is that a function? What
do I mean by that? That if it's used for purposes of
a holiness, then it's exempt. So לשכת פרהדרין Lishkat Parhedrin is not
used for a holy purpose, right? Even though it's in a sanctified
place, it's not used for a holy purpose. It's used for his
habitation. So that kind of קודש, kodesh, oh wait, let me just,
that kind of קודש kodesh would be obligated in מזוזה. mezuzah. But
if it's just a holy used for a holy purpose, like you
know, I don't know, whatever it is, right, like in the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash they're doing their קמיצה. kemitzah.
Isn't it a holy purpose?
I'm sorry? Ah, but that's, but yes,
but you see that this is used for like a mundane function,
right?
But then המאירי, ha-Meiri, listen to this.
Interesting, interesting, two concepts. A מצוה mitzvah is a commandment that doesn't
have a holiness, I mean, the object maybe has holiness, but yeah,
I think you're right.
המאירי, ha-Meiri, you know, like the, right, I mean, maybe on a
spiritual but they're being very technical here, right? So if it's, forget
about its location, it may have to do with its use. Get
that? Maybe the לשכה lishkah may be in a holy place but
its use is something mundane, so that
may need a מזוזה mezuzah as opposed to the קודש, kodesh, the
הר הבית, Har HaBayit, you know, which is not used for דירה.
dirah. That's the one, wait, let me just say this one last
thing, המאירי ha-Meiri says actually... He says for he says if an
area is מקודש *mekudash*, it does not require a מזוזה *mezuzah*, regardless
of how it is used. Interesting. Okay. So so then why does
לשכת פרהדרין *Lishkat Parhedrin* need a מזוזה *mezuzah*? He's saying it may
not be a holy place at all. Because you know because רש"י
*Rashi* is saying essentially he bases it on a רש"י *Rashi* that
the לשכת פרהדרין *Lishkat Parhedrin* was not sanctified. Right? And so the
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* who is not permitted to sit in the
לשכה *lishka*, right, you know, but he can't sit in the בית
המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* but he can stay in here. So remember you
know we so that gets into what we said before where is
opening to mean was it considered holy was it not considered holy
so it gets into that, right? So basically what we're saying is
לשכת פרהדרין *Lishkat Parhedrin* was not נתקדש *nitkadesh*. So
right you know which is why we had that whole thing about
maybe his wife could be there you know whatever.
So that may be the rationale entirely that so that may be
why a holy place does not need a מזוזה *mezuzah* but a
mundane place needs that little bit of קדושה *kedusha* attached to it
to sanctify it as it were.
So that's, are we good?
Should I go on?
Okay. So that's what we got?
Yeah okay. Eight minutes left. Yeah alright fine.
תני בר שמואל בר יהודה תמיה דרבה *Tanei
Bar Shmuel Bar Yehuda Tamei DeRabba*, ששה שערים פטורים מן המזוזה *Shisha
shearim peturim min ha-mezuzah*. Keep close count. One. Six things. בית התבן
*Beit HaTeven*. Two. בית הבקר *Beit HaBakar*. Three. בית העצים *Beit HaEtzim*.
I'm acting like we already talked about all this. בית האוצרות *Beit
HaOtzrot*. שער המדי *Shaar HaMadi*. So what's שער המדי *Shaar HaMadi* is
number five. What is a שער המדי *Shaar HaMadi*?
So it's sort of like a cupola, right? Like it's like made
like a dome.
And now this is an architectural thing. Six. שער שאינו מקורה *Shaar
she-eino mekureh*. An unroofed שער *shaar*. Seven. שער שאינו גבוה י' *Shaar
she-eino gavoah yud*. So a שער *shaar* that's not if it's not
עשרה טפחים *asara tefachim* high. So what was the problem?
Okay. So אמר ליה פתחת בששה וסיימת בשבעה *Amar lei Patachta be-shisha
ve-siyamta be-shiva*. Right? פתחת בשש וסיימת בשבע *Patachta be-shesh ve-siyamta be-sheva*. Right?
You said six things and you said seven. So which is it?
So he says really okay six undisputed ones and one is disputed.
אמר ליה שער המדי תנאי היא *Amar lei Shaar HaMadi tannai hi*.
That's a dispute. דתניא כיפה *De-tanya kippa*. So ר' מאיר מחייב וחכמים
פוטרים *Rabbi Meir mechayev ve-chachamim potrim*. So now we're basically we're going
to deal with is a
if you will
like an archway, right?
So there's this one very good picture in the
ArtScroll. So you know we we have an obligation there we're gonna
talk about in a minute. So עשרה טפחים *asara tefachim* high, right?
But let's say you're gonna have something that's sort of like let's
say this is ארבעה טפחים *arba'ah tefachim* wide. Not drawn to scale.
But let's say it
curves.
The curves, right? So an arch. Part of it is straight, so
it's not like a circle, it's not a tunnel, right? It's an
arch. Now at the top, it's less than four
diameter,
but you know you have bricks because it's like built into a
wall, right? So this would be three, at the top is ten,
this is less than four on top, but the whole thing is,
you know, four, right? And then bricks, bricks, bricks, bricks, bricks. Okay.
So we'll get to that in a second.
Just envision that in your in your mind because we're going to
get back to fourths or or, you know, actually רש"י *Rashi* has
a diagram looks like that tooth over there almost on the left.
So
yeah. Okay. But I mean you basically see what I what I
drew over there. So, okay. So anyway the שער המדי *Shaar HaMadi*
and we're going to get into the specifics as to what they're
disagreeing about
is a מחלוקת machlokes. תנאים *machloket tannaim*. דתניא כיפה *De-tanya kippa* ר'
מאיר מחייב וחכמים פוטרים *Rabbi Meir mechayev ve-chachamim potrim*.
Now we're going to see, you know, where they really disagree. ושוין
שאם יש ברגליה עשרה *Ve-shavin she-im yesh be-ragleiha asara*. So let's say
it's ten high, then it arches, everyone agrees שחייבת במזוזה *she-chayevet be-mezuzah*.
אמר אביי דכולי עלמא גבוה י' ואין ברגליה ג' ולא כלום היא
*Amar Abaye de-kulei alma gavoah yud ve-ein be-ragleiha gimel velo khlum hi*.
So let's say let's say it never has שלשה טפחים *shlosha tefachim*
of you know straight edge, right? So if it's ten but it
has the requisite height but it doesn't in total ten טפחים *tefachim*
but it's never straight for שלשה טפחים *shlosha tefachim* on the ground.
לאו כלום היא *Lav klum hi*. Everyone agrees you don't need a
מזוזה *mezuzah*. אי נמי יש ברגליה ג' ואינה גבוהה י' *Ei nami
yesh be-ragleiha gimel ve-einah gevohah yud*. And even if it has three
straight but it just doesn't go up עשרה טפחים *asara tefachim* of
י' טפחים *yud tefachim* also לאו כלום היא *lav klum hi*. לא
נחלקו אלא בגבוהה י' ויש ברגליה ג' ואין ברחבה ד' *Lo necheleku
ela be-gevohah yud ve-yesh be-ragleiha gimel ve-ein be-rochbah daled*. Just that picture
I drew over there, right? So it has three
straight, it you know goes up to ten, but it arches so
that, you know, at the end of the day you don't have
a width of four. אבל יש בחקוק להשלימה לארבעה *Aval yesh be-chakuk
le-hashlimah le-arba'ah*. But on top, you know, you have bricks. Were you
to like, you know, if you will, peel this away, right? You'd
get a straight edge, right? Meaning, you know, pretend there's no archway,
right? You have the bricks over
there, that'll make it four wide. מר סבר חוקקים להשלים *Mar savar
chokekim le-hashlim*, right? Sort of like, you know, remember you have walls
that extend you know down or walls that extend up like גוד
אחית *gud achit*. Exactly, that's what I was saying. So גוד אסיק
*gud asik*. So sort of like that idea. Do you view it
as if it's, you know, I understand it arches but do you
view it Oh, oh, I guess they're in this room also at
8:25? Oh, both of you?
Okay, let me just- we're late- so you gotta leave now?
Just- give me literally one minute.
We're supposed to- we're supposed to start at 8:25.
Oh, okay. Okay, we'll leave. Anyways, מר סבר חוקקין להשלים ומר סבר
אין חוקקין. That's- that's it. So that's the מחלוקת. machlokes. So whether
you- whether you view it as if you can peel away or
whether you don't. That's- so that's the מחלוקת. Okay, we'll talk from
here tomorrow.